Guide to the Argiculture and Forestry Collection 1828-2005 MS003 MS003 MS003
Cornwall Historical Society
Agriculture and Forestry Collection
1828-2005
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS003
1 linear foot (1 box)
This collection contains information on the history of Cornwall’s farms and forests.
Provenance
This collection was compiled from loose papers found in miscellaneous boxes. Materials were gathered first by local historian E.C. Starr, and then later by members of the Cornwall Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
This collection was compiled from loose papers found in miscellaneous boxes. Materials were gathered first by local historian E.C. Starr, and them later by members of the Cornwall Historical Society. Documents are organized into two archival boxes, one specifically for bound items and the other for general records.
This collection contains information on the history of Cornwall’s farms and forests.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains information on the history of Cornwall’s farms and forests. The collection contains personal items that belonged to Cornwall farmers, such as almanacs and account books, as well as the records of agricultural societies and individual farms. Forestry items are primarily related to the Cathedral Pines and Mohawk State Forest.
Arrangement
Within these boxes, documents are organized alphabetically into sections, where they are organized in chronological order.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Bound Materials
Loose Materials
Forestry -- Connecticut.; Correspondence; Pamphlets; Publications; Account books; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Cornwall Historical Society.
- Bound Materials
  - Almanacs
    - The Christian Almanac, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Christian Almanac, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Connecticut Almanac, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Connecticut Almanac, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Connecticut Almanac, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Family Almanac, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Courant Almanac, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Farmer’s Almanac, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - North Cornwall Grange Records
    - Account Book, 1895-1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Account Book, 1915-1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Membership roll and account book, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Membership roll and account book, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Membership roll and account book, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Membership roll and account book, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Loose Materials
  - Agricultural Societies
    - Connecticut Agricultural Society report on Gold, Hart, Pratt, and Brewster farms, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Union Agricultural Society annual address and transactions, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper article on B.C. Patterson address given to Cornwall Grange, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Notices for series of Dairyman’s Institute Meetings, 1906-1911 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Dairyman’s Institute Meeting programs, 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 6-9)
    - North Cornwall Grange Lecturer’s Program, 1908-1933 (Box 2, Folder 10-17)
    - Article on "Grange’s 50th Anniversary", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Invitation sent to E.C. Starr to Cornwall Grange Roundup, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Connecticut State Agricultural Institute programs, 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
    - Notices for Farmer’s Institute meetings, 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - E.C. Starr’s membership card for the Litchfield County Farm Bureau, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Amended constitution of the Litchfield County Farm Bureau, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Booklet on Housatonic Valley Pomona Grange No. 10, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Housatonic Pomona Grange Hand Book, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Envelope sent to E.C. Starr from Connecticut Department of Agriculture, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cornwall Agricultural Society Fair
    - Poster for first annual field day, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Newspaper story on fair, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Premium lists, 1913-1922 (Box 2, Folder 32-40)
    - Program, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Program, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Memo, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Advertisement, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Ribbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Gold family items
    - Newspaper article on Charles L. Gold’s efforts to increase sheep population, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "Agriculture: A Plea for Reinstatement," by Charles L. Gold, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Letter from C. H. Gold, regarding ice and refrigeration, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Publications
    - "The American Agriculturalist", 1842 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "The Cultivator and Country Gentleman," with an article by Luther H. Tucker, Alger Institute alum, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "The Connecticut Farmer," with image of Harrison H. Ives, Housatonic Valley Institute alum, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "Connecticut Agricultural Experiment", 1909 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "Storrs Agricultural Experiment", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Newspaper article on "Big Drouths In Years Past", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - "Connecticut Agriculture," with listings of Cornwall farms for sale, 19114 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "Extension Service News," with articles on Cornwall, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - "The Hart Farm," by Adella Seelye, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "The Litchfield County Farm Bureau News", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Manuscript, "The Kind of Farming that Pays in Winchester, Goshen, and Cornwall", undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Booklet about Calhoun, Gold, and Harrison dairy farms, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - “How To Choose A Good Cow” advertisement, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Newspaper clipping, "The Decline of Farming in Litchfield County", undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Schools
    - Catalogue of the Cream Hill Agricultural School, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Program for Extension School of Agriculture and Country Life, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Agricultural Miscellany
    - Ribbon from State Agricultural Society, Bridgeport, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Letter of certification for R, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Notes on unspecified photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Forestry
    - Newspaper article about the Cathedral Pines, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Letters from the Connecticut Forest Association officers to members, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 69-70)
    - “Management Plan for the Mohawk State Forest,” by S. E. Parker, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - “The Mohawk Tower Corporation,” notice, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - “History of Mohawk Mountain,” by William Baldwin, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - “History of Clark Hill,” by Harriet Benedict Wadhams, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - “History of Clark Hill,” by Emma Palmer Adams, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - “Sketches of Mohawk Mountain,” by William E. Beese, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - “Mohawk Mountain from the South,” by Mary Brown Clark, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 77)